Lucas Falcão

QA Engineer



linkedin.com/in/lucas-falcão lucasmjj09@gmail.com +55 (81) 99496-7386 https://github.com/lucasperj

About Me

Experienced QA Automation Engineer. Proven record in impacting software development phases, enhancing processes, and ensuring comprehensive execution for team success. Proficient in Manual Testing, Selenium and Cypress for automation testing and recognized for providing support for multiple environments (databases | app servers). Committed to proactive, quality-focused contributions

Education History

Bachelor of technology in Information Systems

Institution: Guararapes University (UniFG)

Year of Graduation: 2024

 Transferred from the Federal Rural University of Pernambuco (UFRPE)

Languages

- Portuguese (Native)
- English (Advanced)
- · Spanish (Basic)

Values

- · Communicative
- Collaboration
- Proactivity
- Leadership
- Teamwork
- Agile Mindset
- · Opinionated nature

Work Experience

QA Engineer

Liferay Latin America, a global company that provides a DXP Software with multiple customizable tools. Feb 2022 to Dec 2023 (1 years, 10 months)

- Test Execution: E2E (end to end), Functional, Regression, UAT, Performance, Upgrade.
- Automation: Lead initiatives with Selenium and Poshi.
- Test Environment Maintenance: Collaborated actively using Ant Apache and Docker.
- Release Analysis: Monitor weekly builds compiled with the help of Jenkins, monitor approval phases with the team.
- CI Monitoring: Analysis of builds, test results imported into TestRail in a combination of different app servers and databases, generation of management reports.
- Feature analysis: Collaborate in the design, planning, manual testing and automation of highly complex initiatives such
 as -
 - Upgrade Report Data via JMX
 - Exporting database partitions
 - Database Partition Migration to PSQL
 - Multiple improvements to Upgrade Report tool
- User Story Refinement: Collaborated on refining user stories, integrating them into development cycles(SDLC).
- Scenario creation and test planning: Scenario creation and test planning: Opportunity to design test cases with the help of decision tables, also in the creation and maintenance of the test plan.
- Bugs creation and tracking: Generally identified through automated or manual testing and addressed in a Jira ticket, tracking bugs with automated boards.
- Bugs Validation: Validate fixed bugs in order of priority and demand.
- Agile Ceremonies Participation: Use tools such as Jira and Confluence for sprint planning, backlog refinement, daily standup and retrospectives.
- Team Communication: Maintain transparent communication via slack, leveraging Git for version control to enhance collaboration and code management.

- · Collaboration and documentation:
 - Mentored a tester who arrived at the company and accompany him through his initial steps in the QA area.
- With help, documented and restructured all of the team's technical and theoretical QA documentation, a result that had an impact at the company level, demystifying upgrade tests and increasing coverage.
- I led meetings in order to looseness and get closer to fellow QAs on US and BR from teams that collaborated with each other

Allocated on the Upgrades team, I excelled in a cooperative, cross-functional environment, collaborating seamlessly with team members in Spain and the United States. My ability to swiftly grasp complex technical concepts and communicate effectively in English made me an ideal fit. I played a key role in creating and executing automated tests using Selenium and Poshi. My proven track record in consistently delivering results, coupled with a commitment to continuous learning, positioned me as a valuable asset to the team. I also led communication efforts within the globally distributed team, contributing to seamless task execution and project alignment.

QA Engineer Intern

Liferay Latin America, a global company that provides a DXP Software with multiple customizable tools. *Mar 2021 to Feb 2022 (10 months)*

- Test Execution: Functional, Exploratory, Regression, Localization, Accessibility, UAT, Upgrades.
- Highlight for intensive manual project using browserstack to test the product on mobile platforms in an urgent initiative for a client in Japan.
- Automation: Collaborate on initiatives with Selenium and Poshi.
- · Release Analysis: Monitor the weekly release build triaged and compiled by Jenkins(with minor supervision).
- CI Monitoring: Build analysis and test results imported into TestRay, generation of comprehensive reports.
- Feature Analysis: Collaborate on design, planning, manual testing and automation on initiatives such as -
 - Kaleo Designer Workflow Migration to React
 - Many improvements to the Calendar feature
 - Help with the initial steps in quality terms of the company's Low Code project
- User Story Refinement: Collaborate on refining user stories, integrating them into development cycles(SDLC).
- Bugs Creation and Tracking: Generally identified through automated or manual testing and addressed in a Jira ticket, tracking with automated boards.
- Bugs Validation: Validate fixed bugs in order of priority and demand.
- Agile Ceremonies: Use tools such as Jira and Confluence to refine the backlog, daily standup and retrospectives.
- Team Communication: Maintain transparent communication via slack, leveraging Git for version control to enhance collaboration and code management.

Allocated on the BPM Team - Workflow squad, that own's a robust and invaluable tool, specializing in crafting customized workflows for clients. Successfully spearheaded the complete migration from JSP and other legacy technologies to React, requiring a parallel migration and redesign of all testing procedures. I stood out for my determination to take on the challenges and succeed with them, also for my highly opinionated nature. I played a key role in creating and executing automated tests using Selenium and Poshi to achieve timely automation goals. My results delivered, combined with a commitment to continuous learning, positioned me as a valuable asset to the team.

Software Test Engineer Intern

CIn - Fade/Motorola Project.

Jul 2020 to Mar 2021 (9 months)

- Implemented effective test strategies, emphasizing Regression and Exploratory testing methodologies.
- Utilized JIRA for raising and tracking change requests on the agile board.
- · Actively participated in Scrum methodology meetings to align testing efforts with development cycles.
- Executed and communicated manual test results, contributing to a robust foundation for manual testing expertise.
- Conducted thorough regression tests post-bug resolution to ensure software integrity.
- Applied standardized test processes to assess both new and existing products, aligning with customer requirements.
- Tracked and reported bugs to the software development team, capturing detailed logs for analysis.

The experience at Motorola provided a strong background in manual testing and valuable insights into test strategy implementation, bug tracking, and collaboration within an Agile framework.

Other Technical Skills

- Linux
- Git | Github
- Docker
- Ant Apache
- Shell Script
- Java
- React | Node.js
- HTML | CSS | JS

- Cypress
- Maven
- Jenkins
- CI | CD practices
- SQL Databases (Mysql | Postgresql | MariaDB | Oracle | DB2 | SQLServer)
- BDD | ATDD
- Agile and Waterfall methodologies